<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-01-11T19:02:35+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Thinking Model</title><subtitle>Everything that is Interesting.</subtitle><author><name>Abhinav Thorat</name></author><entry><title type="html">Attention is all you need with a twist</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Attention-is-all-you-need-with-a-twist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Attention is all you need with a twist" /><published>2025-01-11T17:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2025-01-11T17:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Attention-is-all-you-need-with-a-twist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Attention-is-all-you-need-with-a-twist.html"><![CDATA[<p>Imagine stepping into a movie theater, expecting a relaxing evening of cinematic magic. But as soon as you walk in, you realize this is no ordinary theater, this is the <strong>LSTM Theater</strong>. Instead of plush seats arranged in neat rows facing a giant screen, you’re led to a weird, single file line chair arrangement. Each person stares through a tiny peephole, trying to catch a glimpse of the movie.</p>

<p>The experience only gets stranger. To follow the story, you rely entirely on the person in front of you whispering what they just saw. The catch is to understand the movie You’re expected to jot down notes as fast as you can and pass them along to the person behind you. The result? Chaos.</p>
<center><img src="./assets/img/posts/20250105/lstm.jpg" /></center>

<h2 id="here-are-the-shortcomings-of-this-relic-system">Here are the shortcomings of this relic system:</h2>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>One scene at a time</strong> : You can only process the movie frame by frame [<strong>Sequential Processing</strong>].</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Gossip gone wrong</strong> : By the time someone in the back hears about the climactic car chase, the action’s over and done [<strong>Vanishing Gradient</strong>].</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Memory meltdown</strong> : Keeping track of plot details becomes impossible if the movie is long enough [<strong>Limited Memory Retention</strong>].</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Character confusion</strong> : When the mysterious stranger from the first scene reappears in the finale, you’ve already forgotten who they are [<strong>Long-range Dependency</strong>].</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Slow motion nightmare</strong> : The theater operates like a single-threaded processor, grinding along one scene at a time [<strong>Limited Parallel Processing</strong>].</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>This theater is a maddening relic, functional but incredibly inefficient. Much like its namesake, the <strong>LSTM architecture</strong>, it’s good in some cases but suffers specifically with an information overload, struggling to tell a story with every twist, turn, and moment of suspense.</p>

<h2 id="welcome-to-the-transformer-theatre-a-blockbuster-redefinition-of-cinema-and-ai">Welcome to The Transformer Theatre: A Blockbuster Redefinition of Cinema (and AI)</h2>

<p>Welcome to The Transformer Theatre, a revolutionary cinema that’s changing how we experience movies! As you step through its grand entrance, 
you’ll immediately notice this isn’t your grandfather’s movie house. Gone are the restrictive peepholes and cramped single-file seating. Instead, you’re greeted by a magnificent amphitheater where every viewer
has a perfect view of the entire screen and can freely interact with anyone else in the audience.</p>
<center><img src="./assets/img/posts/20250105/3.jpg" /></center>
<center><small>Generated by Gemini Model with Prompt : Generate an image of Las Vegas Sphere.</small></center>

<h3 id="the-incredible-positioning-system-position-encoding">The Incredible Positioning System [<strong>Position Encoding</strong>]</h3>

<p>As you enter, you receive a special theater pass that’s crucial to your experience. This is the theater’s ingenious <strong>Position Aware</strong> system:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Numbered Seats</strong>: Each seat has a unique number encoded in a special way:
    <ul>
      <li>Your seat number is converted into two different patterns: sine and cosine waves</li>
      <li>These patterns are like musical notes that get higher or lower depending on where you sit</li>
      <li>Even if you’re in seat 100 or seat 1000, you’ll still have a unique position pattern relative to your position in the sequence, ensuring the model understands the order and relationships between all viewers</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Position-Aware Glasses</strong>: You receive special glasses that combine your position information with what you’re watching:
    <ul>
      <li>Every observation you make about the movie is automatically tagged with your position</li>
      <li>When discussing the movie, everyone knows exactly which part you’re referring to</li>
      <li>The position information becomes part of every interaction and discussion</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>This positioning system solves a crucial problem: it helps everyone know where they are in relation to each other and the movie’s timeline, making every interaction position-aware.</p>

<h3 id="the-viewing-experience">The Viewing Experience</h3>

<p>Your group of friends represents what we’ll refer as <strong>Tokens</strong>, each person being a unit of information, like a word in a sentence. The special glasses you wear aren’t just for position awareness; they let you watch both the movie and your fellow viewers simultaneously. This is exactly how the <strong>Attention Mechanism</strong> works, the ability to focus on multiple things at different levels of importance.</p>

<p>During the movie, something fascinating happens. When a dramatic scene unfolds, each person in your group starts doing three things:</p>
<ul>
  <li>You think about what you want to understand about the scene (<strong>Query</strong>)</li>
  <li>You consider what insights you can offer others (<strong>Key</strong>)</li>
  <li>You note down what you actually observed (<strong>Value</strong>)</li>
</ul>

<p>This three-way process is <strong>Self-Attention</strong>. It’s like everyone in the theater being able to tap into each other’s thoughts about the movie, deciding which perspectives are most relevant to their understanding.</p>

<h3 id="the-interactive-experience">The Interactive Experience</h3>

<p>During intermission, your friends naturally split into different discussion circles. One group analyzes the plot twists, another discusses character development, while a third group debates the cinematography. This parallel processing is called <strong>Multi-Head Attention</strong>, different aspects being analyzed simultaneously.</p>

<p>Each viewer keeps a personal notebook [<strong>Feed-Forward Network</strong>] where they process everything they’ve learned from these various discussions. But here’s the clever part, nobody completely overwrites their initial impressions. Instead, they add new insights to their original thoughts, creating what’s known as <strong>Residual Connections</strong>.</p>

<p>There’s a friendly usher walking around [<strong>Layer Normalization</strong>] making sure no discussion gets too heated or too quiet. They keep conversations balanced, just like how AI systems need to keep their internal values in check.</p>
<h3 id="avenger-assemble--multi-head-attention-at-work">Avenger Assemble : Multi-Head Attention at work</h3>
<p>Imagine if, instead of just one person in the theater trying to analyze every aspect of the movie, you had a team of specialists. Each specialist focuses on a different element like plot, visuals, sound, or acting and then they combine their insights for a holistic understanding.</p>

<p>The Transformer splits attention into multiple “heads,” each analyzing different parts of the input sequence. Each head looks at different relationships between words, such as how a word in one part of
a sentence might relate to another word far away. After analyzing the input independently, the results from all heads are combined, giving the model a nuanced understanding of context and relationships.
This scaling enables the Transformer to extract and represent diverse patterns within the data, making it especially powerful for handling complex language structures.</p>
<h3 id="the-two-part-experience">The Two-Part Experience</h3>
<p>The evening at the Transformer Theatre is split into two main parts:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>The First Half [<strong>Encoder</strong>] : This is where you watch the movie and engage in dynamic discussions with others. Everyone in the theater processes the same movie, analyzing details and forming insights. Think of this as the Encoder’s job: it takes the input (the movie) and breaks it down into meaningful components through collective observations.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The Second Half [<strong>Decoder</strong>] : Now comes the creative part. You write your review of the film. As you write, you refer back to your notes from the first half [using Attention to the Encoder] while also keeping track of the review you’ve already written [<strong>Decoder Self-Attention</strong>].</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-brilliance-of-the-causal-language-model-comes-into-play">The brilliance of the Causal Language Model comes into play:</h3>

<p>As you write, you don’t want spoilers from the future! The review you’re crafting must flow logically from one sentence to the next. This mirrors the concept of <strong>Masked Attention</strong> in the decoder. It ensures that when generating the current word, the model only considers words that came before it. For instance, if you’re halfway through a sentence about the plot twist, the model doesn’t “peek” at how the sentence ends, maintaining <strong>causality</strong> in the sequence.
How It All Works Together
The Encoder takes all the rich information from the movie [tokens] and processes it, creating a compressed but meaningful representation of the film’s key elements. The Decoder then uses this representation alongside Masked Attention to craft the review step by step:</p>

<p>While writing each sentence, the Decoder Self-Attention ensures the current word connects logically with the words that precede it.
Simultaneously, the decoder references the encoded movie notes [via Encoder-Decoder Attention] to ensure accuracy and coherence.
This two-part system ensures a smooth, organized review-writing process, just like how the Transformer model excels at tasks like language generation. It combines structured understanding from the encoder with logical, step-by-step storytelling from the decoder.</p>
<center><img src="./assets/img/posts/20250105/absolute.jpg" /></center>

<h3 id="the-magic-of-multiple-viewings">The Magic of Multiple Viewings</h3>

<p>The whole experience repeats itself through multiple showings [<strong>Layers</strong>], with each viewing allowing for deeper understanding and more nuanced interpretations. Each time through, the connections between different aspects of the movie become clearer and more refined.</p>

<p>What makes The Transformer Theatre special is how everyone can instantly share thoughts with anyone else in the room. There’s no need to pass messages down a row of people, every viewer has a direct line to every other viewer, just like how <strong>Transformer</strong> models can directly connect any piece of information with any other piece.</p>

<h2 id="the-revolutionary-impact">The Revolutionary Impact</h2>

<p>As you leave The Transformer Theatre, you realize this wasn’t just any movie night, it was a perfect demonstration of how modern AI processes information. The collaborative viewing experience, the structured discussions, the careful note-taking, and the thoughtful review-writing process all mirror the sophisticated way <strong>Transformer</strong> architecture processes and understands information. But this is just the beginning; the journey is only starting, and it stretches far beyond what we can imagine.</p>

<h3 id="gpt-revolutionizing-the-art-of-language-modelling">GPT: Revolutionizing the Art of Language Modelling</h3>

<p>The Generative Pre-trained Models [<strong>GPT</strong>], much like seasoned movie critics, undergo rigorous preparation before they even begin writing their reviews.</p>

<ul>
  <li>The Pre-training Phase:
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>In this phase, GPT models watch thousands of “movies” (or datasets) from various genres, absorbing intricate patterns, structures, and relationships.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>They learn how characters interact, how stories unfold, and how subplots tie into larger narratives. This phase is unsupervised, meaning the model observes and learns without explicit instructions, developing a rich understanding of language and context.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>The Fine-tuning Phase:
    <ul>
      <li>
        <p>Once pre-trained, these models are fine-tuned with specific goals in mind. For instance, they might specialize in writing film reviews, crafting poetry, or even generating business reports.</p>
      </li>
      <li>
        <p>This phase hones their ability to focus on the task at hand, aligning their output with the desired tone and purpose. Nowadays, these are referred to as Agents, though I’m not sure if they’re here to write, compute, or order a martini shaken, not stirred.</p>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-role-of-attention-in-gpt-models">The Role of Attention in GPT Models</h3>
<p>Generative Pre-trained Transformers owe their success to the Attention Mechanism, which allows them to analyze and synthesize information with unparalleled efficiency. Here’s how it works in the context of GPT:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Context Awareness</strong>: The model remembers and weighs all the relevant parts of a narrative, ensuring coherence and depth.</li>
  <li><strong>Causal Language Modeling</strong>: GPT models generate text one token at a time, leveraging Masked Attention to maintain logical flow.
Dynamic Understanding: By attending to both immediate and long-range dependencies, they can weave a detailed yet contextually rich responses.</li>
</ul>

<p>The foundation of all this innovation traces back to the groundbreaking paper <a href="https://ar5iv.org/pdf/1706.03762">“Attention Is All You Need”</a> by Vaswani et al. This seminal work introduced the Transformer architecture, revolutionizing how machines process and generate language. In the near future, this breakthrough is sure to stand the test of time.</p>]]></content><author><name>Abhinav Thorat</name></author><category term="artificial intelligence" /><category term="large language model" /><category term="generative models" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to Transformer Theatre.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why “Good Enough” Stops You from Achieving “The Great” - The Region Beta Paradox</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/region-beta-paradox.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why “Good Enough” Stops You from Achieving “The Great” - The Region Beta Paradox" /><published>2024-11-09T12:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-11-09T12:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/region-beta-paradox</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/region-beta-paradox.html"><![CDATA[<p>Imagine two people trying to catch a train. One lives a few minutes away from the station, and the other lives much farther. If both happen to miss the train, the person who lives nearby might think, “No big deal, I’ll just wait for the next one,” and sit at the station for 20 minutes. Meanwhile, the person who lives farther away might realize they can’t afford to wait and instead take immediate action—calling a cab, taking another route, or finding an alternative.</p>

<p>Strangely enough, the person who had the greater inconvenience—the one living farther from the station—ends up reaching their destination faster because the situation pushed them to act. This is a perfect illustration of the Region Beta Paradox, where larger challenges often spur more decisive action and greater growth, while smaller issues lead to complacency.</p>

<h1 id="what-is-the-region-beta-paradox-and-how-does-it-work">What Is the Region Beta Paradox, and How Does It Work?</h1>
<center><img src="./assets/img/posts/20241013/psychology.jpg" /></center>
<!-- <center><small>First image of Black Hole at the center of Messier 87 by Event Horiszon telescope.</small></center> -->
<p>The Region Beta Paradox, a concept coined by psychologist Daniel Gilbert, describes the counterintuitive idea that people may respond more quickly and recover faster from intense discomfort than from mild, tolerable challenges. This phenomenon suggests that when a problem is severe, it becomes a clear signal for us to take action, whether by making a change, finding a new strategy, or pushing ourselves harder. However, if the issue is only mildly uncomfortable, we’re often more likely to stay in that “good enough” zone, tolerating suboptimal conditions without feeling the need to act.</p>

<p>The paradox reveals a hidden flaw in our instinct to avoid discomfort. While we naturally seek comfort, this often leads us to settle into situations that are “good enough” instead of pushing us toward something great. The paradox suggests that mild discomfort or moderate dissatisfaction can actually be more detrimental to our progress than outright failure because it doesn’t force us to take the leaps needed for true growth. In other words, a mildly frustrating situation can lull us into inaction, while a more uncomfortable one can be the push we need to break out of our comfort zone.</p>

<h1 id="when-discomfort-drives-change">When Discomfort Drives Change</h1>
<center><img src="./assets/img/posts/20241013/change.jpg" /></center>
<p>Throughout history, we can see the Region Beta Paradox at play, where intense challenges spurred transformative change. Consider the Great Depression of the 1930s: while it brought widespread economic hardship and joblessness, the intense adversity motivated governments, communities, and individuals to enact sweeping changes that redefined modern economies. Franklin D. Roosevelt’s New Deal in the United States, for instance, led to unprecedented government programs and reforms aimed at creating jobs, protecting workers, and stabilizing the economy—measures that would have been hard to achieve without the dire conditions of the time.</p>

<p>Similarly, the Civil Rights Movement in the 1960s was fueled by systemic injustices and violent oppression that African Americans could no longer tolerate. The starkness of segregation and discrimination compelled leaders like Martin Luther King Jr. and countless supporters to risk their lives, resulting in landmark victories like the Civil Rights Act of 1964. The extreme discomfort of living under such conditions galvanized an entire generation to push for rights and equality that reshaped society.</p>

<h1 id="the-region-beta-paradox-in-your-personal-life">The Region Beta Paradox in Your Personal Life</h1>
<center><img src="./assets/img/posts/20241013/choice.jpg" /></center>
<p>Understanding the Region Beta Paradox can be a powerful tool for breaking out of a “good enough” mindset and striving for something truly great in your own life. The first step is to recognize when you’re staying in situations because they’re comfortable enough to tolerate but not fulfilling enough to bring genuine satisfaction. This might show up in various areas: a stable but uninspiring job, a friendship that has grown distant, or a personal goal you haven’t prioritized because your current routine feels “good enough.”</p>
<tweet>Good enough is the enemy of greatness. We tolerate what’s bearable, but true growth often comes when we push through discomfort.
</tweet>
<p>To harness the paradox, start by identifying areas in which you feel slightly dissatisfied or restless. Reflect on whether these areas could improve with small changes or whether they may require a more substantial shake-up. Consider the example of a career: if your job feels comfortable but unchallenging, think about how much further you could go if you pursued a new role, developed a unique skill, or even changed careers entirely. Taking a leap into something more challenging can create the discomfort necessary to push you toward greater growth and fulfillment.</p>

<p>Similarly, in relationships, the Region Beta Paradox suggests that tolerating minor issues can sometimes prevent deeper, meaningful improvements. Instead of allowing small irritations to build up, consider addressing them openly and honestly or even reassessing whether the relationship truly meets your needs. Facing these more significant but potentially uncomfortable questions can lead to a more fulfilling connection, either by resolving issues together or recognizing when it may be time to move on.</p>

<p>Another way to incorporate this concept is by setting stretch goals that take you out of your comfort zone. Aim for milestones that seem slightly beyond your reach—whether it’s running a marathon, learning a new language, or starting a side business. By choosing goals that seem intimidating, you bypass the “good enough” zone and activate the energy and focus needed to achieve something extraordinary. This push for greatness often requires enduring discomfort, but that discomfort can be the catalyst for personal transformation.</p>

<p>Finally, you can apply the Region Beta Paradox by shifting your mindset about discomfort itself. Rather than seeing it as something to avoid, start viewing it as a signal that growth and change are within reach. When you encounter frustration, boredom, or slight dissatisfaction, see these as prompts to make bold decisions rather than remaining in the status quo. <strong>Embracing a bit of discomfort intentionally, rather than waiting for a crisis to force change, can help you transform “good enough” into truly great.</strong></p>]]></content><author><name>Abhinav Thorat</name></author><category term="paradox" /><category term="psychology" /><category term="behaviour" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Catch your train on time.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Navigating Dissonance - Unraveling Complex Relationships in Norwegian Wood</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/navigating-dissonance-unraveling-complex-relationships-in-norwegian-wood.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Navigating Dissonance - Unraveling Complex Relationships in Norwegian Wood" /><published>2024-02-16T07:32:20+05:30</published><updated>2024-02-16T07:32:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/navigating-dissonance-unraveling-complex-relationships-in-norwegian-wood</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/navigating-dissonance-unraveling-complex-relationships-in-norwegian-wood.html"><![CDATA[<p>Haruki Murakami’s Norwegian Wood intricately weaves the tales of characters who grapple with love, loss, and self-discovery. Among them, two contrasting pairs, Nagasawa and Toru, Midori and Naoko, offer nuanced insights into the intricate dynamics of relationships.</p>

<p>Nagasawa, a charismatic and pragmatic figure, epitomizes a hedonistic yet a stoic pursuit of pleasure. His detachment and pursuit of fleeting connections stand in stark contrast to Toru’s introspective and contemplative nature. Nagasawa’s character reflects a hedonistic philosophy, prioritizing immediate gratification over emotional depth. In contrast, Toru seeks meaning and connection in the complexities of human relationships. This dichotomy serves as a lens through which Murakami explores the multifaceted nature of love, questioning whether surface-level connections can fulfill the deeper human need for companionship.</p>

<p>Midori, a vivacious and outspoken character, challenges traditional gender norms. Her boldness and unapologetic authenticity provide a stark contrast to Naoko, who embodies fragility and melancholy. Naoko’s struggles with mental health and the weight of past traumas create a poignant narrative, shedding light on the intricacies of love in the face of personal struggles. Midori’s vibrancy, on the other hand, represents a departure from societal expectations, carving her own path in the pursuit of happiness and connection.</p>

<p>The characters of Midori and Naoko embody contrasting facets of strength and vulnerability. Midori, despite grappling with the misery of her life’s circumstances, emerges as a remarkably strong-headed and vibrant force. Her resilience is a testament to her ability to confront adversity with a spirited demeanor, challenging societal norms and expectations. Midori’s boldness becomes a beacon of strength, allowing her to navigate the complexities of love and life with an unwavering determination. On the other hand, Naoko, with her light-hearted disposition, bears the weight of past traumas and struggles with mental health. Her fragility and melancholy reflect the profound impact of personal tragedies on one’s emotional landscape. Murakami skillfully juxtaposes Midori’s tenacity with Naoko’s internal struggles, painting a nuanced picture of how individuals cope with life’s challenges in their own distinctive ways. Through Midori and Naoko, the novel underscores the multifaceted nature of strength and resilience in the face of adversity.</p>

<p>Toru and Nagasawa, the central male characters in Norwegian Wood, epitomize a striking dichotomy in their approaches to life. Toru, characterized by his emotional depth and introspective nature, places a profound emphasis on relationships and human connections. Throughout the novel, his journey is marked by a quest for meaning in the intricacies of love and companionship. Toru’s emotional landscape, influenced by his experiences and the people he encounters, serves as the compass guiding him through the complexities of human relationships.</p>

<p>In contrast, Nagasawa embodies a pragmatic and goal-oriented mindset, emphasizing the pursuit of life’s external markers of success. His character is driven by a relentless pursuit of pleasure, success, and detachment. Nagasawa’s focus lies in achieving tangible goals, whether academic, professional, or personal, often at the expense of deep emotional connections. His philosophy is rooted in a pragmatic pursuit of life’s pleasures, highlighting the novel’s exploration of the tension between external achievements and internal fulfillment.</p>

<p>The convergence of these characters’ lives unfolds a narrative that transcends the conventional boundaries of love stories. Nagasawa and Toru’s friendship becomes a lens through which Murakami explores the varying manifestations of love — from fleeting connections to enduring companionship. The tension between Midori’s outspokenness and Naoko’s vulnerability challenges traditional portrayals of women in literature, adding layers of complexity to their respective journeys.</p>

<p>As the characters navigate the labyrinth of emotions, Murakami invites readers to reflect on the fluidity of human connections. The novel’s exploration of love’s complexities is not confined to romantic relationships alone but extends to friendships and personal growth. The intertwining narratives of Nagasawa and Toru, Midori and Naoko, create a rich tapestry that captures the spectrum of human experiences, showcasing how love manifests in diverse forms.</p>

<p>In Norwegian Wood, Murakami masterfully dissects the human condition through these characters, illustrating that love is a multifaceted journey shaped by individual choices, desires, and the ever-changing dynamics of human connection.</p>]]></content><author><name>Abhinav Thorat</name></author><category term="book" /><category term="philosophy" /><category term="kafkaesque" /><category term="art" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Comparative Analysis of Relationships in Norwegian Wood.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Beyond the Event Horizon - The Making of the Black Hole Image</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/discovery-of-a-myth-copy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Beyond the Event Horizon - The Making of the Black Hole Image" /><published>2023-04-10T07:32:20+05:30</published><updated>2023-04-10T07:32:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/discovery-of-a-myth%20copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/discovery-of-a-myth-copy.html"><![CDATA[<p>April 10,2019 is a one of the most important date in the research field of astronomy and astrophysics and cosmology, the reason is humans for the first time captured an object which breaks all the rules and barriers of physics that we have understood till now, if it’s not obvious let me clarify, we’re talking about first image of Black Hole.</p>

<p>The first-ever image of a black hole captured the attention of the world in April 2019, and the black hole at the center of the Messier 87 galaxy was named “Powehi” in Hawaiian. “Powehi” means “the adorned fathomless dark creation” in the Hawaiian dialect. The image was a remarkable achievement that defied the laws of physics and showcased a strange phenomenon in the universe. However, why is this discovery such a big deal for humanity? It is because this groundbreaking feat represents a significant step forward in our understanding of the universe, and it provides us with invaluable insights into the mysteries of black holes and the cosmos.</p>

<center><img src="./assets/img/posts/20230410/firstimage.jpeg" /></center>
<center><small>First image of Black Hole at the center of Messier 87 by Event Horiszon telescope.</small></center>

<h2 id="journey-through-time---tick-tick-tick">Journey Through Time - Tick Tick Tick</h2>
<p>Let us embark on a brief journey through time, from the 17th century to April 10, 2019. Along the way, we will pass through significant events such as Newton’s era and World War I, as well as Einstein’s predictions of the phenomenon we will soon witness. So, get ready to take the plunge into the past and witness the groundbreaking discovery that has captured the world’s attention till now.</p>

<p>The incredible story of the first-ever image of a black hole goes back to the early 20th century when the most intelligent person to ever live, Albert Einstein, developed his General Theory of Relativity. Despite working as a clerk in a patent office in Munich, Germany, Einstein proposed a groundbreaking idea about the nature of space and time, including the possibility of the existence of black holes. Later, during World War I, a lieutenant serving on the Eastern front, Karl Schwarzschild, gave perfect solutions to the unsolvable equations of Einstein’s theory, paving the way for our modern understanding of black holes. The remarkable contributions of these two brilliant minds, along with many others, culminated in the discovery of a black hole in the center of the Messier 87 galaxy in April 2019.</p>

<h2 id="is-a-black-hole-black-">Is a Black Hole Black ?</h2>
<p>The basic definition of a black hole is a massive object with an incredibly strong gravitational pull that is so intense that even light cannot escape from it. However, the real question that stands before us is how we managed to capture an image of a black hole. After all, <strong>if light cannot escape its horizon, how can we see it?</strong> The answer lies in the way in which the image was formed through the use of a technique called interferometry. This technique involves combining data from multiple telescopes across the globe, effectively creating a virtual telescope the size of the Earth. The resulting image was the culmination of years of work by a global team of scientists and engineers, and it represents a significant achievement in the history of human discovery. Despite the incredible distance of 55 million light-years between us and the black hole, we have managed to capture a glimpse of one of the universe’s most enigmatic objects.</p>

<h2 id="pale-blue-dot--us-">Pale Blue Dot &amp; Us !</h2>
<p>Despite our many flaws and shortcomings as humans on this pale blue dot we call home, we are capable of incredible feats of scientific exploration and discovery. In the case of the first-ever image of a black hole, we used the entire Earth as a telescope, harnessing the power of interferometry to capture an image of an object located 55 million light-years away from us. The results of this remarkable venture have been nothing short of astounding, providing us with invaluable insights into the nature of black holes and the universe itself.</p>

<tweet>While we may have our faults as a species, our collective curiosity and determination to understand the world around us continue to inspire us to reach for the stars, figuratively and literally. 
</tweet>

<h2 id="sir-isaac-newton-to-world-war-i">Sir Isaac Newton To World War I</h2>
<p>Dating back to the time of Sir Isaac Newton and continuing to this day, our understanding of gravity has been shaped by the idea that two bodies with some mass will attract each other, with the force of attraction being proportional to the product of their masses and inversely proportional to the square of the distance between them.<strong>This concept of gravity, known as Newtonian gravity, provided a framework for understanding the universe in terms of three dimensions: x, y, and z.</strong> However, Newtonian gravity faced numerous challenges over time, such as the issue of the speed of light and the concept of absolute rest. Despite these challenges,</p>

<tweet>Newton remains widely regarded as one of the smartest people to have ever lived, having solved the equations of gravity, even if his research sat in obscurity, literally dusting until Halley urged him to publish.
</tweet>

<p>Nonetheless, gravity remains one of the most challenging problems in both quantum physics and astrophysics, highlighting the ongoing need for new insights and discoveries to advance our understanding of the universe.</p>
<center><img src="./assets/img/posts/20230410/albertnewton.jpg" /></center>
<center><small>PS:Gravity is a Force</small></center>

<p><strong>In 1915, Albert Einstein introduced a revolutionary idea of gravity that challenged Newtonian gravity and explained the universe not in just three, but four dimensions, including the dimension of time.</strong> According to Einstein, the curvature of an object’s geometry changes the shape of the space-time fabric, which results in the gravity we experience. In his address to the Prussian Academy of Sciences in the same year, Einstein unveiled the field equation of gravity. However, this equation was entirely unsolvable and required complex calculations to provide an approximate right answer.</p>

<h2 id="lieutenant-on-eastern-front">Lieutenant on Eastern Front</h2>

<p>It was Karl Schwarzschild, a child prodigy with two research papers published before turning 16 and a PhD before 23, who gave the <strong>simplest solution to Einstein’s unsolvable equation.</strong> While serving as a lieutenant in the German artillery on the Eastern front during World War I, Schwarzschild became aware of Einstein’s theory and started working on it. He made some assumptions to solve Einstein’s equation, including a non-electrically charged, non-rotating, perfectly spherical mass. From this, he derived a geometry that satisfied Einstein’s equation, describing the geometry of space-time around a non-rotating mass like a ball. In doing so, Schwarzschild discovered a strange phenomenon in his equation.</p>

<p>In 1915, Schwarzschild made a groundbreaking discovery by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Derivation_of_the_Schwarzschild_solution">deriving a geometry that satisfied Einstein’s equation</a>, describing the space-time around a non-rotating blob of mass. He found that when the term (+dr²/1-rs/r) is substituted by Rs, the Schwarzschild radius, the space-time curve becomes so intense that not even light can escape its gravity. This was a monumental finding, given that light was believed to be the fastest thing in the universe. Schwarzschild also concluded that if you were to observe an object falling into a black hole, it would appear to slow down and never reach the blob of mass. Instead, the object would appear reddish due to the Doppler shift.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, after only six months, Schwarzschild passed away due to a skin disease he contracted during his service in the war. It’s worth noting that his name, <strong>“Schwarzschild,” is a German surname that translates to “black shield,” a fitting name given his groundbreaking work on black holes and the role they play in shaping the fabric of spacetime.</strong></p>

<h2 id="myth-to-reality">Myth To Reality</h2>
<p>The idea of black holes was finally concluded with the solution to the equations of gravity. <strong>This image provides evidence that the general theory of relativity holds strong and that Einstein’s predictions were accurate.</strong> Black holes are formed from the complete gravitational collapse of a neutral and non-rotating body, resulting in a physical singularity at its center. The Schwarzschild radius is the boundary radius of a black hole of this type. In this picture, the Schwarzschild radius holds great significance. Black holes feed on accretion disks, which is also visible in this image.</p>

<center><img src="./assets/img/posts/20230410/accretion.jpg" /></center>
<center><small>Black Hole Unwrapped</small></center>

<p>An accretion disk consisting of dust and gas rotates chaotically around a blackhole at an incredible temperature of around a million degrees. This disk does not extend to the blackhole due to its significant speed, which is a substantial fraction of the speed of light, and forms an innermost stable orbit. Although blackholes are known to spin, we will use the non-spinning model for the sake of simplicity. <strong>Objects at a specific distance from the blackhole can escape its event horizon, which is the point of no return for light, at a distance of 1.5 times the Schwarzschild radius.</strong></p>

<h2 id="the-first-image">The First Image</h2>

<p>This is how we made the seemingly impossible possible. To delve into some facts, the photons that formed the image were of millimeter wavelengths. These photons had to travel for approximately 50,000 years to escape the event horizon and an additional 55 million years to reach us. This implies that the picture we’re seeing is roughly 55 million years old! One can only speculate what might be happening there right now.</p>

<p>Moreover, the Earth’s atmosphere proved to be the biggest obstacle for these millimeter wavelength photons, as the vapor in our atmosphere could easily absorb them. This is why eight of the driest observatories were used to receive this data. To put the amount of data collected into perspective, it was around 8 petabytes (1 petabyte equals 1 million gigabytes). In other words, the data collected is equivalent to a lifetime of selfies and pictures of 40,000 people!</p>

<center><img src="./assets/img/posts/20230410/gargantua.jpg" /></center>
<center><small>Gargantua from Movie Intersteller - 2014</small></center>

<p>This moment is truly monumental in the history of mankind. Although this image may fall short of our expectations, we can remember the blurry black and white pixel image of Pluto from 1996 and compare it to the beautiful image we received in 2017. It’s not far-fetched to imagine that we’ll soon be able to observe a Black Hole image that is just as breathtaking as Gargantua from the movie Interstellar.</p>]]></content><author><name>Abhinav Thorat</name></author><category term="astronomy" /><category term="astrophysics" /><category term="cosmology" /><category term="history" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Single neuron perceptron that classifies elements learning quite quickly.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What if women ruled the World?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/What-if-Women-Rule-The-World.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What if women ruled the World?" /><published>2022-12-10T13:32:20+05:30</published><updated>2022-12-10T13:32:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/What-if-Women-Rule-The-World</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/What-if-Women-Rule-The-World.html"><![CDATA[<p>It has been a long due thought experiment for me to analyze what Our world would look like if ‘Women rule the world?’, especially when Covid strategy of New Zealand appeared to be most successful which is govern by  prime minister Jacinda Ardern - a female prime minister, not that I’m robbing credit of others who were involved in effective policy implementation, but this has intrigued me to fondle this question in deeper manner.</p>

<h2 id="a-proposition-worth-considering">A proposition worth considering!</h2>

<p>It is a fascinating thought experiment to consider what the world would be like if women were in charge. While it is impossible to know for certain what the outcome would be, there are some potential advantages and disadvantages that could arise from such a scenario.</p>

<p>One potential advantage of a world ruled by women is that it could lead to a more cooperative and empathetic society. Studies have shown that women tend to have better communication and social skills than men, and are more likely to prioritize the well-being of others over their own individual interests. This could lead to more peaceful and harmonious relationships between individuals, communities, and nations.</p>

<h2 id="patriarchal-and-matriarchal-societies-in-animals">Patriarchal and Matriarchal societies in Animals.</h2>

<center><img src="./assets/img/posts/20221012/bon-vs-chimp.jpg" width="480px" />
<figcaption>Physical similarity of Chimpanzees and Bonobo apes.</figcaption></center>

<p>For example, the bonobo monkeys provide a good analogy for what a society ruled by women might look like. Unlike their aggressive and hierarchical cousins, the chimpanzees, bonobos are known for their peaceful and cooperative behavior. They form strong bonds with one another and engage in activities such as communal childcare and group hunting. This has earned them the nickname of “hippie apes” because of their laid-back and nurturing lifestyle.
Bonobo monkeys use sex to relieve tension in social group as a form of greeting and a way to celebrate.</p>

<p>In a world ruled by women, it is possible that similar values of cooperation and empathy would be promoted, leading to a more harmonious and egalitarian society. This could also result in a more balanced distribution of resources and opportunities, as women are often at a disadvantage when it comes to accessing education, healthcare, and other essential services.</p>

<h2 id="human-matriarchal-societies">Human Matriarchal Societies</h2>

<p>One example of a human society that has embraced a more cooperative and empathetic approach is the Mosuo people of China. This matriarchal society is characterized by a strong emphasis on female leadership and the importance of relationships and community. Women hold the positions of power and make important decisions for the community, while men are responsible for more practical tasks such as farming and hunting. This has resulted in a peaceful and harmonious society, in which conflicts are resolved through mediation and dialogue rather than violence.</p>

<tweet>One potential advantage of a world ruled by women is that it could lead to a greater focus on environmental sustainability.</tweet>

<p>Women are often more attuned to the needs of the natural world, and are more likely to prioritize conservation and preservation over short-term profit and growth. This could lead to more sustainable and eco-friendly policies, as well as a greater awareness and appreciation of the natural world.</p>

<p>For example, the indigenous Aka people of Central Africa provide a good example of a society that has a deep connection to the environment. This matrilineal society is led by women, who are responsible for the management of natural resources such as forests and rivers. They have developed a sustainable way of life that is in harmony with the natural world, and have been able to maintain a rich biodiversity in their lands.</p>

<h2 id="potential-drawbacks">Potential Drawbacks</h2>

<p>Potential drawbacks to a world ruled by women. One concern is that it could lead to a more paternalistic and controlling society, in which women seek to protect and regulate the behavior of others in order to maintain order and stability. This could result in a loss of individual freedom and autonomy, as well as a stifling of creativity and innovation.</p>

<h2 id="threat-to-individual-freedom--gender-stereotypes">Threat to Individual Freedom &amp; Gender Stereotypes</h2>

<p>One example of a society that has embraced a more controlling and paternalistic approach is the Hutterite communities of North America. These Anabaptist sects are led by women, who have the authority to make important decisions for the community and to regulate the behavior of its members. This has resulted in a highly structured and controlled society, in which individual freedom is heavily restricted and conformity is emphasized.</p>

<p>Another potential disadvantage of a world ruled by women is that it could lead to a reinforcement of gender stereotypes. In a society where women are the dominant gender, there may be pressure to conform to traditional feminine roles and expectations, such as being nurturing and submissive. This could limit the ability of women and men to explore their full range of talents and interests, and could also prevent men from participating fully in society.</p>

<p>Additionally, such gender stereotypes could lead to a lack of diversity and representation in leadership positions. If traditional feminine roles and expectations are prioritized, women who do not fit these norms may be marginalized and excluded from positions of power. This could result in a homogenous and narrow-minded leadership, lacking the diversity of perspectives and experiences necessary for effective decision-making.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Well it will really difficult to start a new World order or simulate such experiment but making society gender neutral can definitely give pros from the both matriarchal and patriarchal rules. Also I don’t support Radical feminism, it’s just an attempt to showcase what difference equal contribution will make on human society to propel us into the Future.</p>]]></content><author><name>Abhinav Thorat</name></author><category term="Politics" /><category term="Sociology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Analatical perspective along with analogy from closest genetical match of Chimpanzee and Bonobos.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Who owns the copyright for an AI generated creative work?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/AI-and-intellectual-property.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Who owns the copyright for an AI generated creative work?" /><published>2022-09-20T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2022-09-20T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/AI-and-intellectual-property</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/AI-and-intellectual-property.html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I was <a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-features/nirvana-kurt-cobain-ai-song-1146444/">reading an article</a> about a cool project that intends to have a neural network create songs of the late club of the 27 (artists that have tragically died at age 27 or near, and in the height of their respective careers), artists such as Amy Winehouse, Jimmy Hendrix, Curt Cobain and Jim Morrison.</p>

<div class="video" position="relative" padding-bottom="25.25%" padding-top="30px" height="0" overflow="hidden">
    <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tjzOzuKQhSM" position="absolute" top="0" left="0" width="100%" height="100%">
    </iframe>
 </div>

<p>The project was created by <a href="https://overthebridge.org">Over the Bridge</a>, an organization dedicated to increase awareness on mental health and substance abuse in the music industry, trying to denormalize and remove the glamour around such illnesses within the music community.</p>

<p>They are using Google’s <a href="https://magenta.tensorflow.org">Magenta</a>, which is a neural network that precisely was conceived to explore the role of machine learning within the creative process. Magenta has been used to create a brand new “Beatles” song or even there was a band that <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2019/08/yachts-chain-tripping-is-a-new-landmark-for-ai-music-an-album-that-doesnt-suck/">used it to write a full album</a> in 2019.</p>

<p>So, while reading the article, my immediate thought was: who owns the copyright of these new songs?</p>

<p>Think about it, imagine one of this new songs becomes a massive hit with millions of youtube views and spotify streams, who can claim the royalties generated?</p>

<p>At first it seems quite simple, <em>Over the Bridge</em> should be the ones reaping the benefits, since they are the ones who had the idea, gathered the data and then fed the neural network to get the “work of art”. But in a second thought, didn’t the original artists provide the basis for the work the neural network generated? shouldn’t their state get credit? what about Google whose tool was used, should they get credit too?</p>

<p>Neural networks have been also used to create poetry, paintings and to write news articles, but how do they do it? A computer program developed for machine learning purposes is an algorithm that “learns” from data to make future decisions. When applied to art, music and literary works, machine learning algorithms are actually learning from some input data to generate a new piece of work, making independent decisions throughout the process to determine what the new work looks like. An important feature of this is that while programmers can set the parameters, the work is actually generated by the neural network itself, in a process akin to the thought processes of humans.</p>

<p>Now, creative works qualify for copyright protection if they are original, with most definitions of originality requiring a human author. Most jurisdictions, including <a href="https://www.wipo.int/wipolex/en/details.jsp?id=1319">Spain</a> and <a href="https://dejure.org/gesetze/UrhG/7.html">Germany</a>, specifically state that only works created by a human can be protected by <a href="https://www.wipo.int/copyright/en/">copyright</a>. In the United States, for example, <a href="https://copyright.gov/comp3/chap300/ch300-copyrightable-authorship.pdf">the Copyright Office has declared</a> that it will “register an original work of authorship, provided that the work was created by a human being.”</p>

<p>So as we currently stand, a human author is required to grant a copyright, which makes sense, there is no point of having a neural network be the beneficiary of royalties of a creative work (no bank would open an account for them anyways, lol).</p>

<p>I think amendments have to be made to the law to ensure that the person who undertook all the arrangements necessary for the work to be created by the neural network gets the credit but also we need to modify copyright law to ensure the original authors of the body of work used as data input to produce the new piece get their corresponding share of credit. This will get messy if someone uses for example the #1 song of every month in a decade to create the decade song, then there would be as many as 120 different artists to credit.</p>

<tweet>In a computer generated artistic work, both the person who undertook all the arrangements necessary for its creation as well as the original authors of the data input need to be credited.</tweet>

<p>There will still be some ambiguity as to who undertook the arrangements necessary, only the one who gathered the data and pressed the button to let the network learn, or does the person who created the neural network’s model also get credit? Shall we go all the way and say that even the programmer of the neural network gets some credit as well?</p>

<p>There are some countries, in particular the UK where some progress has been made to amend copyright laws to cater for computer generated works of art, but I believe this is one of those fields where technology will surpass our law making capacity and we will live under a grey area for a while, and maybe this is just what we need, by having these works ending up free for use by anyone in the world, perhaps a new model for remunerating creative work can be established, one that does not require commercial success to be necessary for artists to make a living, and thus they can become free to explore their art.</p>

<tweet>Perhaps a new model for remunerating creative work can be established, one that does not require commercial success to be necessary for artists to make a living.</tweet>

<p><img src="./assets/img/posts/20210420/post8-rembrandt2.jpg" alt="The next Rembrandt" />
<small><a href="https://www.jwt.com/en/work/thenextrembrandt">The Next Rembrandt</a> is a computer-generated 3-D–printed painting developed by a facial-recognition algorithm that scanned data from 346 known paintings by the Dutch painter in a process lasting 18 months. The portrait is based on 168,263 fragments from Rembrandt’s works.</small></p>]]></content><author><name>Abhinav Thorat</name></author><category term="opinion" /><category term="copyright" /><category term="creativity" /><category term="neural networks" /><category term="machine learning" /><category term="artificial intelligence" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As neural networks are used more and more in the creative process, text, images and even music are now created by AI, but who owns the copyright for those works?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Single Neuron Perceptron</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/single-neuron-perceptron.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Single Neuron Perceptron" /><published>2019-06-26T01:02:20+05:30</published><updated>2019-06-26T01:02:20+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/single-neuron-perceptron</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/single-neuron-perceptron.html"><![CDATA[<p>The human brain is an intricate web of billions of interconnected neurons that allow us to process information, make decisions, and perform complex tasks. This remarkable ability has inspired the creation of artificial neurons, like the perceptron, which mimic biological neurons in a simpler form. These artificial neurons are the building blocks of Artificial Intelligence (AI), enabling machines to learn and evolve.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-a-perceptron">What is a Perceptron?</h2>

<p>Imagine a single neuron,a tiny but essential unit in the vast neural network of your brain. It activates when it receives signals, processes them, and decides what to do next. Similarly, a perceptron is the most basic computational unit of a neural network. Its invention by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank_Rosenblatt">Frank Rosenblatt</a> in the late 1950s laid the foundation for modern AI.</p>

<p>Think of it as a decision-making machine. It takes inputs, applies some rules, and generates an output. Despite its simplicity, the perceptron unlocks the doorway to understanding more complex systems.</p>

<p><img src="./assets/img/posts/20210125/Perceptron.png" alt="Perceptron Illustration" /></p>

<h3 id="breaking-down-the-perceptron">Breaking Down the Perceptron</h3>

<p>To understand a perceptron, let’s peek inside its mind. It starts with a set of inputs, let’s call them \( x_1, x_2, x_3 \)and their corresponding weights \( w_1, w_2, w_3 \). These weights reflect the importance of each input. The perceptron combines these inputs by multiplying each with its weight and summing them up.</p>

<p>
For example, consider:<br /><br />

- Inputs: \( x_1 = 1, x_2 = 2, x_3 = 3 \)<br />
- Weights: \( w_1 = 0.5, w_2 = 1, w_3 = -1 \)<br /><br />

The perceptron computes the weighted sum: <br />

\[
(x_1 \times w_1) + (x_2 \times w_2) + (x_3 \times w_3)
\]
Plugging in the values: <br />

\[
(1 \times 0.5) + (2 \times 1) + (3 \times -1) = 0.5 + 2 - 3 = -0.5
\]
</p>
<p>Next, the perceptron applies an <strong>activation function</strong>, which determines the output. If we use a linear activation function (i.e., the value remains as it is), the output here is (-0.5). This output can help classify data, for example, negative values could indicate Type A, and positive values Type B.</p>

<h3 id="the-magic-of-learning">The Magic of Learning</h3>

<p>Here’s where the magic happens. A perceptron isn’t just about calculating outputs, it’s about learning. It adjusts its weights based on errors in its predictions, using a process called <strong>backpropagation</strong>.</p>

<p>When we train a perceptron, we provide it with a dataset of known inputs and outputs (a training set). The perceptron compares its predictions to the actual outcomes, calculates the error, and tweaks its weights. This iterative process, guided by <strong>gradient descent</strong>, helps the perceptron improve over time, enabling it to make accurate predictions even for unseen data.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The magic starts with backpropagation, where the perceptron “learns” by iteratively adjusting its weights to minimize errors.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If you’re curious about gradient descent, I highly recommend <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aircAruvnKk&amp;list=PLZHQObOWTQDNU6R1_67000Dx_ZCJB-3pi">this video series by 3Blue1Brown</a>, which explains it beautifully.</p>

<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>

<p>As the perceptron learns, it converges to a solution, a line that separates the data into distinct categories. While perceptrons are excellent for solving linear problems, they have their limitations. For instance, they can’t handle non-linear problems.</p>

<p>Modern neural networks, however, build upon the perceptron. By combining multiple perceptrons across layers and introducing advanced neuron types, they tackle a vast array of complex problems. From identifying faces to predicting stock prices, these networks are transforming the world as we know it.</p>

<p>Starting with a perceptron is like learning the alphabet before writing a novel, it’s simple yet foundational. And for me, it was the perfect entry point into the incredible world of Machine Learning.</p>]]></content><author><name>Abhinav Thorat</name></author><category term="machine learning" /><category term="neural networks" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Single neuron perceptron that classifies elements while learning efficiently.]]></summary></entry></feed>